# Joel Schumacher

# Short Profile

Please have a look at my portfolio for detailed information about 40+ of my personal projects I have made over the last 10 years, including 18 game jam games, a few larger games, small game/graphics engines, level editors, a web server, a text editor, a LuaJIT profiler, and numerous other tools and libraries:

https://theshoemaker.de/projects

My portfolio shows that I have been highly motivated to build a diverse range of things for a long period of time. I do not back away from problems that seem too large or too difficult, but rather I am intrigued by them and I have always carried this attitude into my professional work as well.

# **Work Experience**

Ericsson GmbH Germany

Developer

02/2019-present

- Developed and maintained a Diameter Signaling Controller (a router for signaling in mobile networks) using C++ on Linux
- Developed customer and developer tooling using Python
- Maintained a large legacy code base and fixed numerous bugs in a distributed application while regularly using tools like gdb, strace, tcpdump, etc.
- Added support for Diameter over TLS using OpenSSL
- Initiated and led migration to C++11: Evaluated adoptability of new features, ported source code and offered guidance on modern usage of C++
- Ported application to Kubernetes:
  - Part of the initial team that led the migration and laid the groundwork
  - Replaced proprietary components for e.g. metrics, inter-process communication, databases, configuration management, etc. with technologies like Prometheus, PostgreSQL, REST (HTTP)

#### Institute for Man-Machine Interaction

**RWTH Aachen University** 

Student Assistant

04/2016-03/2018

Developed a microservice web framework based on Flask and gRPC in Python

#### Institute for Software & Tools for Computational Engineering

**RWTH Aachen University** 

Teaching Assistant

10/2013-03/2014

Taught "Introduction to Programming" exercise classes for computational engineering and physics students (C++)

## Education

## **RWTH Aachen University**

Germany

Completed 39 credits towards Master of Science, Physics

10/2016-04/2018

Focus of Study: Condensed Matter Theory

# RWTH Aachen University

Germany

Bachelor of Science, Physics

10/2011-09/2016

Bachelor's thesis: Symmetry Breaking and Transition to Chaos in Binary and Rate Networks at the Institute for Computational and Systems Neuroscience & Theoretical Neuroscience at the Forschungszentrum Jülich

# **Skills**

Languages: German (native), English (fluent)

Programming Languages: C++, Python, Lua

Software: Linux, Git, Docker, Kubernetes, Meson, CMake, PostgreSQL

Libraries/APIs: Linux/POSIX, OpenGL/GLSL, OpenSSL, io\_uring, Boost ASIO, HTTP/1.1, SQLite